[MUSIC]
[음악]
So we've talked at great length about how to form predictions using different types
여러 추천 시스템으로 예측 구성하는 법을
of recommender systems.
자세히 다뤄봤습니다
But a question is, how do we assess the difference in performance for
이제 궁금한 건 여러 시스템의
these different systems we might consider using?
성능 차이를 어떻게 평가할지입니다
Well imagine we want to recommend products to a new parent, and
새로 부모가 된 사람에게 상품을 추천한다고 하죠
this is the set of all possible products that we might recommend.
추천할만한 상품이 많습니다
And a user likes a subset of these products which are represented by these
그중 사용자는 자홍색 사각형으로
magenta squares.
표시한 일부만을 좋아합니다
And our goal, of course, is to discover the products that the user likes
우리의 목표는 사용자의 이전 구매만 보고
from the purchases that they've made.
뭘 좋아하는지 알아내는 것입니다
Because we don't actually know which products they like, that's our goal, okay?
어떤 상품을 좋아하는지 사실 모르는데 알아내는 게 우리 목표죠?
So a question is, why don't we just use something like classification accuracy to
그렇다면 분류 정확도로 추천 시스템의 성능을
measure the performance of a recommender system?
측정하면 되지 않을까요?
So in this case, we could think about just counting how many items we
이 경우 몇 항목을 좋아할 거라,
guessed that they liked versus they did not like and
좋아하지 않을 거라 추측했는지 세서
compare that to how many of those items they actually liked versus did not like.
실제 좋아하고 안 좋아한 항목수를 비교합니다
So Carlos talked about using that type of metric
카를로스가 감성분석 사례 연구에서
when he was talking about the sentiment analysis case study.
이런 종류의 기준도 있음을 설명했습니다
But the issue here is actually multifold.
하지만 문제는 사실 하나만이 아닙니다
One is the fact that we really care more about what the person
One is the fact that we really care more about what the person 그중 하나는 사용자가 뭘 좋아하는지가
liked than what they didn't like and often we're faced with very imbalanced classes.
뭘 좋아하지 않는지보다 중요하고 데이터가 불균형 클래스일 경우가 많다는 점입니다
So, for example, there are lots and lots and lots of products out there,
예를 들어 수많은 상품이 존재하는데
but typically a user's only gonna like a very small subset of them.
사용자는 그중 아주 일부만을 좋아하죠
And so if we use this type of metric, we can get very good accuracy
이런 종류의 기준을 사용한다면 사용자가 아무 것도
by just saying that the user won't like any of the items.
좋아하지 않는다고 선언함으로써 아주 높은 정확도를 달성할 수 있습니다
So not recommending anything will get
아무 것도 추천하지 않는 게
pretty good performance according to this metric.
이 기준에 따르면 꽤 좋은 성능을 보여줍니다
But another issue is something else which
또 다른 문제는 이런 여러 결정을 내리는데
relates to the cost of making these different decisions.
드는 비용과 연관되어 있습니다
So often we're gonna assume that the user has a limited attention span,
사용자가 제한된 주의 범위를 가졌다고 가정해서
and so we can only recommend a certain number of items for that user to look at.
특정 항목 몇 개만 보도록 추천합니다
So there is a much larger cost if out of this very small
그러므로 이렇게 몇 안 되는 추천 목록 중
set of items we're allowed to recommend to this person there's no liked item.
사용자가 안 좋아하는 게 껴있다면 비용이 커집니다
That has a much higher cost than if we missed some of the user's liked items
이건 추천 상품 목록에서 사용자가 좋아하는
in this set of recommended products.
항목 몇 개가 빠진 것보다 훨씬 높은 비용입니다
So instead, we're gonna talk about a different metric,
그러므로 다른 기준을 알아볼 텐데
or different metrics which are called precision and recall.
정밀도와 재현율이라 불립니다
Let's start by discussing recall.
재현율부터 알아보죠
So for a given a recommender system, it's gonna recommend some set of products to
어떤 추천 시스템이 상품 목록을 추천하는데
me, and I'm highlighting those by the colored pictures.
이를 컬러로 강조하죠
So this is a recommended item.
이게 추천 항목입니다
This is a recommended item, this is a recommended item and so on.
이것도 추천 항목, 이것도 추천 항목이죠
Where as the grayed out pictures are items that were not recommended for me.
흑백 그림들이 추천되지 않은 항목입니다
Okay, so I haven't done a comprehensive annotation here, but
이해를 위한 주석이 있지는 않지만
hopefully you get the picture.
무슨 말인지 아시리라 믿습니다
And when I'm measuring recall,
재현율을 측정할 때
what I'm gonna look at is I'm gonna look at all the items I liked.
좋아하는 모든 항목을 살펴보고
So all of these magenta boxes.
자홍색 상자들이죠
And I'm gonna ask how many
그중 얼마나 많은 항목이
of the items that I liked were actually recommended to me.
저에게 추천됐나를 봅니다
And so I'm gonna compute that fraction, so let's do that.
분수 계산을 한번 해보죠
So each of the magenta boxes, so here's one that was recommended to me.
자홍색 상자에서 이게 처음으로 추천됐고
Two that were recommended to me,
이게 두 번째로 추천됐으며
three that were recommended to me out of five items that I like.
좋아하는 항목 5개 중 세 번째로 추천됐습니다
So the recall, is three-fifths.
재현율은 3/5입니다
And so recall is gonna measure how much a recommended set of items cover
재현율은 추천된 항목 목록에서
the things that I'm interested in, things that I actually like.
관심있는 물건이 얼마나 포함됐는지 측정합니다
On the other hand, there's something called precision.
이제 정밀도를 봅시다
When we talk about precision what we're gonna look at is
정밀도를 논할 땐
all of the recommended items.
모든 추천 항목을 봅니다
So when we're talking about recall our world when we were measuring
재현율을 논할 땐
this fraction here was looking at the magenta boxes.
자홍색 상자에서 분수를 계산합니다
That was the world that we looked at everything else could disappear from
나머지는 모두 화면에서
the slide.
없어도 됩니다
But when we are talking about precision, we're gonna look at all the recommended
정밀도를 논할 땐 모든 추천 항목만을 보고
items and then everything else can disappear from the slide.
나머지는 화면에서 없어도 됩니다
So the recommended items are highlighted by these green boxes.
추천 항목은 초록색 상자로 강조돼있습니다
What we are going to look at out of the recommended items if that is our entire
추천 항목에서 살펴볼 건 그중 몇 개나
world What fraction of those items were items that I liked?
제가 좋아했는지입니다
Okay, so in this case there are one, two,
이 경우 하나, 둘,
three items that I liked and were shown and
세 개를 좋아했고
a total of 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7,
총 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9,
8, 9, 10, 11 items that were shown.
10, 11 항목이 있습니다
So this would be the precision.
이게 정밀도가 됩니다
And so when we're thinking about precision we're thinking about basically how much
즉 정밀도란 쉽게 말하자면 봐야 할 전체 개수와
garbage do I have to look at compared to the number of items that I like.
좋아하는 항목의 개수를 비교한 것입니다
So, it's a measure of when I have a limited attention span,
제한된 주의 범위를 가졌을 때 얼마나 많은 노력을
how much am I gonna be wasting my efforts on products that I do not like?
안 좋아하는 상품에 쏟아야 하는지 나타내는 척도입니다
[MUSIC]
[음악]